M. L. Parrish Collection of Victorian Novelists, 1806-1958 (bulk 1830s-1930s ): Finding Aid C0171
Manuscripts Division
- Series 1: Artwork and Manuscripts, 1700-2999; 32 boxes; 141 items; 12 Volumes
  - Subseries 1B: Bound Manuscripts, 1700-1951; 4 boxes; 138 items; 12 Volumes
    - Hughes Family, 1800-1809; 1 item
      - "Photograph Album", 1800s; 71; 1 item
        Hughes family photograph album.
    - Kingsley, Charles, 1819-1875, 1800-1871; 4 items
      - "Hunting in Ireland", 1834; 1 item (Item 73)
        Contains 5 original pen-and-ink drawings for "Hunting in Ireland." Four of the illustrations have captions in pen, two have titles "Brought up" and "Brought down." One drawing is inscribed "Feb. 3, 1834 Kingsley."
      - "The Lord Coming to his Temple", 1800s; 1 item (Item 74)
        Annotated galley proof, n.d.
      - "The Lord is at Hand", circa 1846; 1 item (Item 75)
        Manuscript sermon, in the hand of Kingsley. "Preached at Eversley 1846 1849."
      - "Manuscript Sermons", circa 1845-1871; 1 item (Item 76)
        Three autograph manuscript sermons dated Sept. 4, 1845 (Genesis xiii 6.); Sunday Apr. 26, 1846 (Matthew XIII 31.32); and Feb. 5, 1871 (Matthew vols. 13.14).
      - "Sermons", circa 1853-1863; 77; 8 Volumes (Volume 1, Volume 2, Volume 3, Volume 4, Volume 5, Volume 6, Volume 7, Volume 8)
        Manuscript sermons, in hand of Kingsley.
    - Kingsley, Frances Eliza Grenfell, 1814-1891, 1841 May 5-1886; 2 items
      - "Lilian", 1841 May 5; 1 item (Item 79)
        Manuscript notebook containing 2 poems by Fanny Kingsley. Other title "O'Conner's Child, or, The Flower of Love lies bleeding."
      - "Scraps of Letters &c.", 1886; 1 item (Item 80)
        Letterbook and Manuscript notebook, kept by "Fanny G. Kingsley, Feb 6th 1886." Contains miscellaneous writings and letters to family and friends dated from 1880-84.
    - Kyd, 1856 or 7-1937, 1883; 1 item
      - "12 Original Character Studies from 'The Old Curiosity Shop' Drawn in Colours by Kyd", circa 1883; 1 item (Item 39)
        Contains 12 watercolor drawings by Kyd, a pseudonym for Joseph Clayton Clarke. Clarke executed a number of watercolor drawings of "Characters of Dickens." Contains drawings entitled: "Nell"; "Grandfather Trent"; "Quilp"; "Sampson Brass"; "Sally Brass"; "Dick Swiveller"; "The Marchioness"; "Coalin"; "Short"; "Mrs Jarley"; "Kit"; "Mr Chuckster."
    - Lever, Charles James, 1806-1872, 1800-1868; 1 item
      - "Charles Lever's Memorandum Book", 1800s; 1 item (Item 81)
        Manuscript book of miscellaneous notes and accounts, undated.
      - "The Bramleighs of Bishop's Folly", circa 1868; 150; 2 Volumes (Volume 1, Volume 2)
        Lever's original manuscript for the novel "The Bramleighs of Bishop's Folly," written in Charles Lever's small neat hand, and with his alterations and corrections, on rectos only, some finger-soiling and marks, occasional marginal repairs, one leaf partially excised, some pencillings in a later hand (mostly numbers); bound in 2 volumes, with green crushed morocco by Riviere & Son. Probably a late draft of Lever's sixty-nine chapter novel, which appears to be largely complete but without chapters twenty-eight to thirty inclusive, and possibly with one or two other pages lacking.
    - Lewes, George Henry, 1817-1878, 1870-1879; 3 items
      - "Problems of Life and Mind", 1870s; 1 item (Item 84)
        Autograph manuscript of "Problem III: The Sphere of Sense and Logic of Feeling," with notes in George Eliot's handwriting as arranged by her for publication, undated.
      - "Problems of Life and Mind", 1870s; 1 item (Item 83)
        Autograph manuscript of "Problem IV: The Sphere of Intellect and the Logic of Signs," with notes in George Eliot's handwriting as arranged by her for publication, undated.
      - "Problems of Life and Mind", 1870s; 1 item (Item 82)
        Autograph manuscript together with some annotated proof copy.
    - Lytton, Edward Bulwer Lytton, Baron, 1803-1873, 1817-1871; 5 items
      - "Autograph Letter Signed", circa 1826; 1 item (Item 86)
        Concerns his poetry, possibilities for publication of some of his poetic works, thoughts on Cambridge, and his activities in Knebworth. Autograph letter (1 leaf) addressed "Knebworth-Nr Welwyn Sunday" to "My dear Sir" and bound together with a typed transcription (4 leaves). The date 1826 is written in pencil, in a later hand, at the top right corner of fol. 1.
      - "Autograph Letters", circa 1833-1871; 1 item (Item 85)
        Bound collection of typewritten and autograph letters. Together with engraved portraits (3) of Lytton.
      - "The Caxtons", 1849; 1 item (Item 87)
        Signed autograph manuscript of the preface, together with 2 versions of the title page. This preface was not used in the published version.
      - "Eugene Aram", 1831; 88; 3 Volumes (Volume 1, Volume 2, Volume 3)
        Autograph Manuscript
      - "The Pilgrims of the Rhine; Godolphin", 1849-1850; 1 item (Item 7)
        Autograph manuscript of the preface and the prefatory poem of "The Pilgrims of the Rhine," with tear sheets of text as printed (27 pp.). Together with the autograph manuscript of the preface to "Godolphin," with tear sheets of text as printed (10 pp.). Includes 1 ALS from L. W. Bangs to G. W. Childs concerning the manuscripts, dated 17 June 1880.
      - "Poetical Attempts", circa 1817-1819; 1 item (Item 89)
    - Madeira, Betty Campbell, 1890-1899; 1 item
      - "Scrapbook", 1890s; 1 item (Item 1)
        Scrapbook of photographs (both family pictures and souvenir pictures) and newspaper clippings, chiefly concerning the guests for the Dinner Party and Ball Masque at the Madeira home. Includes newspaper photo of a young Morris Parrish, captioned "Dinner Party before the Ball Masque at the home of Mr. and Mrs. Percy Madeira." Some photographs by "E.J. Reilly Phila.," "Reilly & Way, Keith Theatre Building, Philadelphia." Persons identified: Savage Landor and S. Weir Mitchell, Richard Harding Davis, undated.
    - Parrish, George Dillwyn, 1820-1871, Compiler, 1860-1909; 1 item
      - "Scrapbook", circa 1860-1909; 1 item (Item 2)
        Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and printed broadsides concerning Philadelphia local history, Philadelphia Quakers, book auction sales, railroad accidents, etc. Compiled by George Dillwyn Parrish.
    - Parrish, Morris Longstreth, 1867-1944, 1900-1945; 3 items
      - "Dormy House", 1917-1945; 6; 3 Volumes (Volume 1, Volume 2, Volume 3)
        Guest books, kept by Parrish and others, of visitors to Dormy House, in Pine Valley, New Jersey. Includes signatures of guests, plus, photographs, autograph and typewritten letters, notes, artwork, newspaper clippings, magazine tear sheets, and other printed ephemera. Final handwritten entry dated Oct. 23rd, 1945."
      - "Scrapbook of Photographs", 1900s; 1 item (Item 4)
        Scrapbook of photographs, mostly of an older Morris Parrish partaking in recreational activities.
      - "Scrapbook", circa 1937-1841; 1 item (Item 5)
        Scrapbook of ephemera. Includes clippings about Parrish's collection of Victorian Novelists; printed invitations and announcements from "The Philadelphia Club"; typed letters and printed material concerning Parrish's honorary degree from Princeton, dated 1939; clippings, invitations, and announcements of exhibitions from the "Library Company of Philadelphia," etc. Newspaper clippings from the "Philadelphia Record," "Times Literary Supplement," "Philadelphia Inquirer," etc.
      - "Scrapbook", circa 1904; 1 item (Item 3)
        Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and various typewritten pages of poetry and songs. Other topics include Yale and Princeton football, Samuel L. Parrish and Morris L. Parrish, and other Parrish family. Material pasted down in a "Mark Twain's perforated interleaved Scrap Book, patent number 477,050 ..."
    - Perry, Kate, circa 1810-1901, 1871; 1 item
      - "Commonplace Book", 1871; 1 item (Item 90)
        Commonplace book, kept by Miss Kate Perry, containing entries on Charles Dickens and Mr. Thackeray.
    - Quiller-Couch, Arthur Thomas, Sir, 1863-1944, 1897; 1 item
      - "Letters of Quiller Couch to Colvin", 1897; 1 item (Item 126)
        Bound collection of signed autograph letters from Couch to Colvin regarding details of the forthcoming publication of "St. Ives." Each letter accompanied by a typed transcription.
    - Reade, Charles, 1814-1884, 1800-1889; 27 items
      - "Courier of Lyons", 1850s; 1 item (Item 103)
        Hermann Vezin's manuscript copy of a play translated by Reade. Contains hand drawn set designs, undated.
      - "Draft of a Contract for 'Put Yourself in his Place", circa 1868; 1 item (Item 93)
        Original draft, in the hand of Charles Reade, of the contract with William Conant Church and Francis P. Church of Sheldon & Co., for the publication in "Galaxy Magazine" of Reade's story "Put yourself in His Place."
      - "Dora: a Pastoral Drama.", 1870s; 1 item (Item 104)
        Autograph manuscript bound together with the printed version, undated.
      - "Duodecimo Digest 2.", 1800s; 1 item (Item 96)
        Signed notebook, kept by Reade, containing notes for various works, undated.
      - "The Eighth Commandment", 1850s; 1 item (Item 13)
        Manuscript sheets of various sizes, being portions of "The Eighth Commandment," rough drafts of other portions with corrections, and some paragraphs not published. Also includes sheets of fair copy (3) with corrections by Charles Reade, undated.
      - "Foul Play", circa 1883; 1 item (Item 14)
        Autograph manuscript drafts of the fourth and fifth acts of "Foul Play," with annotated clippings of the text pasted down throughout.
      - "General Rolleston in Foul Play", circa 1868; 1 item (Item 105)
        Manuscript copy of the part of General Rolleston in the play "Foul Play," with annotation in pencil in a later hand, possibly the hand of a Newton Griffith who signed his name in pencil on fol. 16v. Exhibition ticket from "The Victorian Era Exhibition, London, 1897, Drama Section V.E.E.-D.S. 276," laid in.
      - "Gold", circa 1851-1852; 1 item (Item 106)
        Part of the original autograph manuscript.
      - "Griffith Gaunt", 1860s; 1 item (Item 10)
        Incomplete autograph manuscript of "Griffith Gaunt."
      - "Griffith Gaunt, or Jealousy: a Drama in a Prologue and Four Acts", 1875; 1 item (Item 15)
        Autograph manuscript together with some printed excerpts (clippings) from "Griffith Gaunt," pasted down throughout.
      - "Griffith Gaunt, or, Jealousy", 1869; 1 item (Item 91)
        Extra illustrated copy compiled by Attorney William D. Booth who represented Charles Reade, Charles Dickens, Wilkie Collins, and other literary and theatrical lights in the American law courts, with his clients original autograph letters. Includes ALS from Charles Reade (9); ALS from Wilkie Collins (5); ALS from Charles Dickens (1); and others (12); Miscellaneous manuscript. by Booth (2); printed texts of 3 offending articles; a printed reply from Reade; newspaper accounts of the trial and other pieces. Also includes other correspondence, mostly on theatrical matters from Bateman Crout, Laura Keene (regarding a copy of the playbill for April 14, 1865 and a piece of her stage gown stained with Lincoln's blood), Augustin Daly, E. H. Sothern, William H. Florence, & others.
      - "It's Never Too Late to Mend: a Drama in Four Acts", circa 1865; 1 item (Item 144)
        Charles Reade's copy of an annotated prompt book for "It's Never Too Late to Mend." Later interleaved with extensive autograph stage instructions by William Seymour.
      - "Jack of All Trades: a Mechanic's Story", circa 1854-1857; 1 item (Item 16)
        Complete autograph manuscript of "Jack of all Trades," contained in 5 notebooks (78 p., in the hand of the author; the balance in the hand of his copyist, J.G. Saunders, c. 1854-1857). Both scripts are heavily corrected by Reade.
      - "Kate Peyton, or, Jealousy: a Drama in a Prologue and Four Acts", 1883; 1 item (Item 15)
        Laid in the Charles Reade manuscript of "Griffith Gaunt," held by the Library's Manuscripts Division, under the accession number AM 1982-71 and in the collection C0171. "Printed for private circulation." Written in pen on front cover. London: J.C. Durant, Clement's house, Clement's Inn passage, Strand, W.C.
      - "The Lyons Mail", 1800s; 107; 3 Volumes (Volume 1, Volume 2, Volume 3)
        Typescript of a play with autograph corrections.
      - "Masks and Faces", circa 1879; 1 item (Item 108)
        Manuscript copy of a play by Reade.
      - "Miscell[aneous] Femina", 1800s; 1 item (Item 99)
        Signed notebook, kept by Reade, containing miscellaneous notes pertaining to female characters and fiction, undated.
      - "Notebook", 1800s; 1 item (Item 94)
        Notebook, kept by Reade, containing notes for "America." Contains notes pertaining to slavery and attitudes towards blacks in America, undated.
      - "Notebook", 1861 July 3-1862; 1 item (Item 98)
        Signed notebook, kept by Reade, containing miscellaneous notes pertaining to characters and fiction, kept while at Oxford.
      - "Notebook", 1800s; 1 item (Item 95)
        Signed notebook, kept by Reade, containing "old notes for 'Cloister and the Hearth." Contains notes of incidents of travels, saints of the time, books, words and phrases, etc. for use while writing his book, undated.
      - "Notes for Hard Cash", 1800s; 1 item (Item 97)
        Signed notebook, kept by Reade, containing notes for "Hard Cash," undated.
      - "Octavus Lex", 1850s; 1 item (Item 100)
        Signed notebook, kept by Reade, containing miscellaneous notes pertaining literary property, copyright, etc., undated.
      - "Passbook", 1871-1875; 1 item (Item 92)
        Bank passbook, kept by "Charles Reade Esq."
      - "The Perilous Secret", circa 1883-1884; 1 item (Item 17)
        Incomplete autograph manuscript. A large portion probably written from dictation, with corrections and additions in Reade's hand.
      - "The Practical Advertiser", circa 1869; 1 item (Item 101)
        Signed notebook, kept by Reade, containing miscellaneous notes and clippings pertaining advertisements for wine, furniture, etc., undated.
      - "Reade's Picture Book & Dictionary", 1800s; 1 item (Item 102)
        Signed notebook, kept by Reade, containing miscellaneous notes and clippings pertaining to "odd stories," "odd fellows," etc. "Caroli Pict et Dict Lib," written on front cover, undated.
      - "Shilly Shally, or, Ralph the Heir", circa 1872; 109; 1 item
        Two sets of original manuscript sheets (folded) for Acts 1 and 2.
      - "Shilly Shally", circa 1871; 1 item (Item 11)
        Autograph manuscript of "Shilly Shally," Reade's unauthorized play based on the 1870 novel "Ralph the Heir," by Anthony Trollope, sheets tipped in. Contains portions of galley proofs with autograph corrections.
      - "Single-heart", 1880s; 1 item (Item 18)
        Incomplete autograph manuscript with corrections, undated.
    - Scott, Walter, Sir, 1771-1832, 1800-1809; 1 item
      - "The Pirate", 1800s; 1 item (Item 110)
    - Smith, Miss M., 1800-1809; 1 item
      - "East Lynne", 1800s; 1 item (Item 111)
        Manuscript, in unknown hand, of a play based on Wood's novel "East Lynne," undated.
    - Stanley, Henrietta Maria Stanley, Baroness, 1807-1895, 1860-1874; 1 item
      - "Guestbook", 1860-1874; 1 item (Item 112)
        Manuscript book of dinner guests kept by Baroness Stanley. Names included novelists and literary figures, nobility, political figures, etc. Newspaper clippings (2) regarding Stanley's dinner guests, tipped in at front.
    - Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1850-1894, 1800-1894; 21 items
      - "The British Grenadiers; The Brown Maid and Other Pieces", 1880s; 1 item (Item 114)
        Autograph music manuscript by Stevenson. Contains three short compositions: "The British Grenadiers," The Brown Maid," and "Believe Me."
      - "Draft of a Contract: Between Robert Louis Stevenson of Vailima Apia, of the First Part and the Deutsche Handels und Plantagen Gesellschafft &c of the Second Part", circa 1892-1893; 1 item (Item 22)
        Original autograph draft of a contract for the complete construction of an addition to the "House of Vailima," with annotations in Stevenson's hand. The draft is accompanied by an undated document of the detailed specifications, written in another hand, and signed in full by R.L.S. Vailima, 1892 and two representatives of the "Haupt-Agentur der Deutschen Handels- & Plantagen--Gesellschaft der Südsee-Inseln zu Hamburg."
      - "Forest Notes", 1880s; 1 item (Item 118)
        Printed proof with autograph corrections of an article by Stevenson printed in "Cornhill Magazine," 33 (May 1876).
      - "Hester Noble's Mistake, or, A Word from Cromwell", 1800s; 1 item (Item 119)
        Original autograph manuscript draft of a play (Act I, scenes 1-8).
      - "Hotel Tivoli", 1894; 1 item (Item 120)
        Receipt from the Hotel Tivoli in Apia Samoa which Robert Louis Stevenson has dated "25 4 94" for "3/= Cash" and signed in full. The three entries are in pencil. "Bechyne" is written in pencil, in another hand, on the verso.
      - "Ille Terrarum", 1800s; 1 item (Item 20)
        Signed autograph manuscript in pencil of the poem "Ille Terrarum." Together with a calligraphic manuscript copy, in unknown hand. Also includes an engraved portrait plate of Stevenson by S. Hallyer at front.
      - "In the Highlands, In the Country Places", 1800s; 1 item (Item 121)
        Autograph manuscript leaf of miscellaneous verse. Includes "In the Highlands, In the Country Places" (5 lines); and other "Verse jottings" (23 lines) said to be an early draft of "Over the Hand is April," undated.
      - "The Mother", 1880s; 1 item (Item 123)
        Autograph manuscript of a poem, undated.
      - "Original Manuscript and Letters", circa 1878; 1 item (Item 21)
        One leaf of autograph manuscript from "The Cruise of the Casco," undated. Together with three signed autograph letters to Charles Baxter from Stevenson.
      - "The Plague Cellar", 1864; 1 item (Item 124)
        Autograph manuscript of a novelette concerning Edinburgh at the time of the plague. Written by Stevenson at a very early age.
      - "Preface to 'The Merry Men,'", 1880s; 1 item (Item 122)
        Autograph manuscript, written in pencil, of the unpublished preface to "The Merry Men," undated. Together with typed transcription
      - "Random Memories: rosa quo locorum", 1894; 1 item (Item 125)
        Autograph manuscript of an essay. Later published in "Essays of travel."
      - "Robert Louis Stevenson as a Musician", circa 1886; 1 item (Item 113)
        Bound set of signed autograph letters by Stevenson to Miss Una A. Taylor at Bournemouth, concerning his musical attempts. Together with an original manuscript of a musical composition by Stevenson. Written at Bournemouth.
      - "Robert Louis Stevenson: His Classic Reply to the Request of an Autograph Collector", circa 1892; 1 item (Item 115)
        Signed autograph letter from Stevenson, Vailima, Upolu, Samoa. Together with two portraits of Stevenson and a post office receipt from Vailima, dated March 14, 1892 and signed by Stevenson.
      - "Strange Case of Dr Jekyll and Mr Hyde", 1885; 1 item (Item 116)
        Original proof slip of the title page as originally intended and submitted for approval by the printers. Stevenson edited out the initials and substituted in his own autograph the words "Robert Louis." Includes other annotations in unknown hand.
      - "Strange Case of Dr Jekyll and Mr Hyde", circa 1886; 117; 1 item
        Unpublished and canceled portion of the original autograph manuscript of "Strange Case of Dr Jekyll and Mr Hyde," with an autograph letter written by the author on the reverse of the manuscript, and addressed to his cousin, Robert Alan M. Stevenson. Also includes a copy of the first London edition as published by Longmans, Green, and Co.
      - "Their Laureate to an Academy Class Dinner" and "Late in the Night in Bed I Lay", 1800s; 1 item (Item 23)
        Autograph manuscript of two poems. Together with typewritten copy bound in.
      - "To a Gardener", 1800s; 1 item (Item 24)
        Autograph manuscript of a poem. Together with tear sheet of printed version.
      - "To Rosabelle, etc.", 1880s; 1 item (Item 128)
        Autograph manuscript of miscellaneous verse. Titles include "Cherish thou, O love, thine unknown lover ..." (11 lines); "To Rosabelle" (5 lines).
      - "Walking Tours", 1880s; 1 item (Item 129)
        Corrected proof copy.
      - "Weir of Hermiston", 1800s; 1 item (Item 25)
        Autograph manuscript of three early drafts of the beginning of the first chapter of his unfinished romance "Weir of Hermiston," undated. Together with typewritten comparison of each with the published version.
    - Stevenson, Thomas, 1818-1887, 1835-1836; 1 item
      - "Journal ", 1835-1836; 1 item (Item 130)
        Journal kept by "Thomas Stevenson, Civil Engineer, 1838." pertaining to woodwork, masonry, ironwork, etc. Bookplates of Jerome Kern, John Wm. Roy Crawford, Henry E. Gerstley; From the Library of Robert Louis Stevenson at Vailima.
    - Ternan, Mrs. Thomas, 1802-1873, 1835; 1 item
      - "Memorials of America", circa 1835; 1 item (Item 131)
        Scrapbook presented to Frances Eleanor Jarman Ternan, the mother of Ellen Ternan. Contains many announcements of forthcoming plays, portraits, and newspaper clippings of Mr. and Mrs. Ternan's and Marie's theatre appearances in America, Canada, and England. The album was presented by Sara and John Frost of Philadelphia who also state that the poems which are inserted are by T.L. Ternan.
    - Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863, 1852; 1 item
      - "Letter and Drawings", 1852; 1 item (Item 132)
        Bound volume containing an autograph letter from Thackeray, signed with initials and dated 1852. Together with two original pencil sketches: a half length figure resembling a character from "The Virginians"; sketch of Napoleon in characteristic pose, beside two faces of Italian brigands. Also includes an original pen-and-ink sketch for the figure of Mr. Osborne in the illustration "Mr. Osborne's welcome to Amelia"; another sketch of Mr. Osborne in pencil, with two partly finished figures on same sheet.
    - Thirkell, Angela Mackail, 1890-1961, 1951; 12 Volumes
      - "The Duke's Daughter", 1951; 133; 12 items (Volume 1-6, Volume 7-12)
        Autograph manuscript of "The Duke's Daughter," written in pencil in 12 notebooks.
    - Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882, 1800-1909; 6 items
      - "Australia and New Zealand", 1873; 137; 2 Volumes (Volume 1, Volume 2)
        Corrected page proofs in unknown hand. London: Chapman and Hall.
      - "Calendar of Anthony Trollope Letters in the Parrish Collection", 1900s; 1 item (Item 134)
        Typed index of the Trollope correspondence found in the Parrish Collection, compiler unknown.
      - "Contract Concerning 'Ayala's Angel", 1881 August; 1 item (Item 139)
        Autograph agreement with Chapman and Hall publishers regarding "Ayala's Angel."
      - "Death of Commodore Goodenough", 1800s; 1 item (Item 26)
        An autograph manuscript of his Letter XVIII, "The Death of Commodore Goodenough." Written on 5 pp., royal tissue paper in pencil and 4 pp. royal paper in ink, signed at the end. Approximately 3,300 words. Each leaf is marked "Duplicate" and on the verso of the last leaf is a note to that effect, also giving the title, n.d. Together with a corrected galley proof.
      - "An Eye for an Eye", 1870s; 1 item (Item 138)
        Complete autograph manuscript of "An Eye for an Eye," with annotations and corrections. Written in 1870 but not published until 1879.
      - "Letters", circa 1839-1882; 135; 3 Volumes (Volume 1, Volume 2, Volume 3)